创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness,
随着一声爆炸
and then, bang--
诞生了无尽膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在揭秘这个诡异
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
震撼 神秘莫测的地方
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
我们所谓的《宇宙》
of a place we call "The Universe."
地球上 液体就在我们周围
On Earth, liquids are all around us,
甚至在我们体内
even inside of us.
然而我们的世界却与众不同
But our world is not like others.
我们举目浩瀚宇宙间的恒星及行星
When we look at the stars and planets of our vast cosmos,
液体其实是相当罕见的
liquids are actually very rare.
当我们发现有液体时
And when we do find liquids,
其怪模怪样地流动在怪异的世界里
they flow in strange ways, on bizarre worlds.
这种环境是我们在地球上无法创造的
It's an environment where nothing that we can build here on Earth
是片刻都无法承受的
could withstand that for more than a fraction of a second.
新发现将永远改变我们对我们液体宇宙的
New discoveries are forever changing what we know
翻腾 沸腾问题的认识
about the churning, bubbling matter of our liquid universe.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：HDC字幕组 调校：晴天 招募Q号: 76846146
历史频道 - 宇宙 第4季第9集 液体宇宙
The History Channel - The Universe s04e09 Liquid Universe
液体几乎覆盖了地球表面的四分之三
Liquids cover nearly 75% of the Earth's surface.
我们看到它们从地下渗出来
We see them oozing from the ground
从天上落下来
or falling from the sky.
我们操控它们为我们的城市供能
And we manipulate them to power our cities
为我们的引擎供油
and fuel our engines.
不过宇宙的大部分地方不是这个样子
But this is not the way of most of the rest of the universe.
液体只占全部物质中很小一部分
Liquids only make up a tiny fraction of all matter.
宇宙大部分是由气体构成的
Most of the universe consists of gas,
不管是星际气体 - 恒星之间的气体
either interstellar gas, the gas between the stars,
还是恒星里面的气体
or the gas within the stars themselves,
还有行星的大气
or the atmospheres of planets.
其它存在的东西就是固体材料了
The other stuff that exists is solid material.
行星就是固体材料构成的
Planets are made out of solid material.
但还是存在少量的液体
But there's really very little liquid.
它确实是宇宙中最难得的
And it's exactly what's most rare in the universe
似乎也是最重要的
that seems to be the most important.
要是宇宙间没了液体
If there were no liquids in the universe,
我真不知道会不会出现生命
I actually doubt that there would be life,
至少像我们在地球上所了解的生命
at least life as we know it here on Earth.
看看其它行星系 或许有其它形式的生命
Looking in other planetary systems, there may be other forms of life
并不利用液体 某种形式的流体
that don't use liquidity, fluidity in some way,
不过此刻 很难想象它是怎么运作的
but right now, it's difficult to imagine how that would work.
我们在宇宙什么地方能找到液体呢？
So where in the universe do we find liquids?
究竟怎样才能让它们存在呢？
And what does it take for them to exist at all?
唯有某些特殊的地方
Only in certain special locations
温度压力恰到好处
where the temperatures and the pressures are just right
你才能得到液体
do you get liquids.
那些条件恰到好处的特殊的地方之一
And one of those special places where the conditions are just right
就在土卫六上 土星最大的卫星
is on Titan, Saturn's largest moon.
土卫六包裹着厚厚的大气层
Titan is wrapped in a thick atmosphere,
密度是地球的50倍
50 times denser than Earth's,
但是在朦胧橙色的天空下 远处昏暗的太阳光
but underneath the hazy orange sky, dimly lit by a distant Sun
主宰着土星美景
and dominated by a stunning view of Saturn,
湖泊波光粼粼
lakes glisten.
如果我们在土卫六上有个摄像头的话
If we had a webcam on Titan
我们就会远眺景色
and we were just looking out on the scenery,
你会以为是在地球上
you could think you were on Earth,
要不是画面中有个温度计
unless there was a thermometer in the image
你看到温度在零下几百度
and you saw that the temperature was hundreds of degrees below zero.
严酷的零下290度是千真万确的
A cruel 290 degrees below zero to be exact.
液体不是水 而是甲烷
And the liquid isn't water, but, rather, methane.
当我们考量我们太阳系里的世界时
When we think about the worlds of our solar system,
只有两个世界在其表面存在有液体
there's only two worlds that have liquids at their surface,
低密度的流动液体会形成湖泊
low-density flowing liquids that could form lakes.
那就是有水的地球以及有甲烷的土卫六
And that's Earth with water and Titan with methane.
但如何才能让地球上的气体
But how can something that's a gas on Earth
变成土卫六上的液体的呢？
be a liquid on Titan?
土卫六肯定不同于地球
Titan is certainly not quite Earth.
最大的不同之处就是温度
And the biggest difference is really the temperature.
土卫六距离太阳非常遥远
Titan is so much further away from the Sun
只能接收到少得可怜的能量
that it receives very little energy,
使其成为了极其寒冷的世界
and that makes it a very, very cold world.
那就意味着同样的元素
And that means that the same elements
我们在地球上看到的会在土卫六上表现得完全不同
that we have on the Earth behave very differently on Titan.
你可以想象土卫六上的情景
You can imagine a scene like this on Titan.
液体拍打岸边
But the liquid that's lapping up on the shore
那是液态甲烷 一种透明的液体
is liquid methane, a clear liquid,
或许会有点微风 就像我们今天在这里感觉到的一样
maybe a very tiny gentle breeze like the one we're feeling here today
会有一点小波浪
with just tiny waves coming up,
岸边的白色东西是冰
and the whitish stuff that makes the shore is water ice.
严格说 冻结的水坚如石头
It's literally frozen water as hard as rock.
我们考虑石头和水时
So when we think of rock and water,
在土卫六上 要把冰看作是石头
on Titan, think of water ice as the rock
液态甲烷看作是液体
and liquid methane as the liquid.
显然 在这么低的温度下 液态水就变成固态的冰了
Clearly, at such a low temperature, liquid water turns into solid ice.
不过不管物质采用何种形态 -
But which state any type of matter takes--
液态 固态 或气态 -
liquid, solid, or gas--
都必须牵涉到每个分子
has to do with how the individual molecules,
其基本构件相互作用的情况
its building blocks, are interacting.
这有点像一群羊
It's a bit like how a flock of sheep
在不同条件下的不同反应
will respond differently to different conditions.
这群羊可以被看作是每一个原子或分子
These sheep can be thought of as individual atoms or molecules,
比如水分子
like molecules of water.
宛如水分子一样 它们可以有各种形态
And just like molecules of water, they can be in different states.
比如现在 它们簇拥在一块
For example, right now, they're kind of clustered together.
它们很少走动
They're not moving around very much.
它们被圈了起来
They're penned in.
那就像固态的水 - 冰
That's like solid water, ice.
在固态下 分子与自己的近邻圈在一起
In a solid, the molecules are really penned in by their nearest neighbors.
它们根本不能移动太多
They're not allowed to move much at all.
水沸腾蒸发成蒸汽时
When water boils and steams into a vapor,
它会从液态变成气态
it changes phases from liquid to gas.
在气态下 其内部的粒子
In a gas, the constituent particles,
原子或分子
the atoms or molecules,
到处游荡 一派混乱
are all wandering around in a kind of chaotic way,
它们往往是随着温度的升高而活动加速
and they tend to move faster if the temperature is higher.
羊群游荡在开阔的原野里
And sheep wandering around in a wide-open field,
自由自在 随心所欲
free to wander every which way they want,
它们不一定呆在一起
they won't necessarily stay together.
它们可以去这里或那里
They might go off in one direction or the other.
那就像是羊的气态状况
That's like a gaseous state of sheep.
它们彼此远离
They're far from one another,
彼此之间有很大的空间
but there's a lot of space between them.
它们的行为无拘无束
Their motions are unconstrained.
然而液体 如水就是一种魔术
But liquid like water is magic.
它是一种不稳定的物质状态
It's a state of matter in limbo,
介于固态的坚实结构
somewhere between the rigid structures of a solid
与气态的无序散射之间
and the random scatter of a gas.
在液态下 原子或分子
In a liquid, the atoms or molecules
好像受制于其邻居
are somewhat constrained by their neighbors.
它们相互之间稍有一点错位
They might pass each other up a little bit,
但它们趋向一起流动
but they tend to flow together.
羊群里的羊
When sheep are in a flock,
在牧羊人的控制下
kind of constrained by the herders
一起从一个地方流到另一个地方
and flowing along from one place to another,
那可以看作是液体
that can be thought of as a liquid.
它们可以相互有点错位
They can pass each other up a little bit,
但它们基本上不会与其邻居离开得太远
but they're basically not wandering too far away from their nearest neighbors.
它们是一起行动的
They're all going together.
它们始终随大流 可以这么说
They're all going with the flow, so to speak.
在土卫六上 寒冷的温度
On Titan, the frigid temperatures
让甲烷分子粘在一起形成液态
keep methane molecules stuck together in a liquid form.
它们的行动犹如羊群
They're moving like sheep in a flock.
在地球上 甲烷是一种天然气
On Earth, methane is naturally a gas
其分子四处游荡宛如那些自由放养的羊群
with its molecules floating around like those free-ranging sheep.
要将其变成液体
To transform it to a liquid
让甲烷分子像羊群一样
so that the methane molecules are like a flock,
科学家需要将它们挤压在一起
scientists need to squeeze them together
用上普通地面压力的300倍
with 300 times normal surface pressure.
地球上甲烷的一个主要用途
One of the main uses of methane on Earth
就是取暖做饭
is for heating and cooking,
所以甲烷是很好的能源
and so methane is a great source for power,
不管是作为燃料还是某种能源
whether it's heat or some kind of propulsive power.
液态甲烷是一种很好的能源
Liquid methane is such a great source of power
航天局正在测试它作为潜在的新火箭燃料
that NASA is testing it as a potential new rocket fuel.
主发动机点火 升空
Main engines up and burning and liftoff
目前 航天器发射升空
Currently, spacecraft launch into orbit
燃料罐里装的是液态氢
on the backs of fuel tanks filled with liquid hydrogen.
因为它比液态氢更轻更稠密
Because it's lighter and denser than liquid hydrogen,
发射燃烧甲烷将更加便宜
launches burning methane could be cheaper.
和液态氢一样 液态甲烷燃烧容易
And like liquid hydrogen, liquid methane combusts readily
因为有氧的存在
because of the presence of oxygen.
但是在土卫六上 因为大气中缺乏氧气
But on Titan, because the atmosphere lacks oxygen,
甲烷难以点燃
methane isn't flammable.
地球有氮和氧
So Earth has nitrogen and oxygen,
土卫六有氮和甲烷
Titan has nitrogen and methane.
奇怪的是太阳系里唯一的两个世界
And it's curious that these are the only two worlds in the solar system that
都将氮作为大气层里的主要气体
have nitrogen as their dominant gas in the atmosphere.
因此在那个意义上 土卫六是我们的姐妹星
So in that sense, Titan is our sister world.
氧在土卫六上将是危险的爆炸性气体
Oxygen would be a dangerous explosive gas on Titan,
因为周围都是甲烷
because it's surrounded by methane,
同样甲烷在地球上是危险的爆炸性气体
the same way that methane is a dangerous explosive gas on Earth,
因为我们周围都是氧气
because we're surrounded by oxygen.
土卫六上 液态甲烷会聚集成湖
On Titan, the liquid methane collects in pools,
有些大如五大湖区
some as large as the Great Lakes.
土卫六的湖区在其北极地区
The lake country on Titan is the northern polar regions,
湖泊众多
enormous number of lakes.
我们看到南部有一个湖
We see one lake in the south.
我们真的不明白为何所有的湖泊都北移
We don't really understand why all the lakes moved north
只留下一个在南部
and left one behind in the south.
为何南部没有更多的湖泊呢？
Why aren't there more lakes in the south?
最近的探索有可能提供了重要的线索
A recent discovery may have provided an important clue.
2009年8月 研究人员发现
In August 2009, researchers detected
风暴云突然出现在土卫六赤道附近
a sudden appearance of storm clouds around Titan's equator.
这可能意味着液态甲烷
This could mean that liquid methane
貌似地球上的水循环
mimics the water cycle on Earth,
水在一个地方的湖泊里蒸发出来
where water evaporates from lakes in one area
然后降雨到另一个地方的湖泊里
and then rains to form lakes in another.
在地球上沙漠地区
In the desert landscapes of Earth,
你偶然会看到少雨的地方豪雨如注
you have occasional cloudbursts where it rains very hard
大水冲过干旱的山谷
and the water rushes through the dry valleys.
不过土卫六大部分地区是甲烷沙漠
But the vast majority of Titan is sort of a methane desert,
一旦下起雨来 一场倾盆大雨
and when it does rain, it's a real cloudburst,
你会在其表面看到巨大的河流
and you have a huge flow over the surface.
所以我们确实认为甲烷能够
So we actually think that in terms of the ability of methane
侵蚀和切割出土卫六上的沟渠和山谷
to erode and carve channels and valleys on Titan,
非常类似于水能够
it would be very similar to the ability of water
切割出地球上的山谷
to carve valleys on the Earth.
湖泊集中在北部的原因之一
One reason lakes are pooling in the north
可能是因为该地区正在经历
could be because that region is experiencing
一个很长的雨季
a very long rainy season.
土星环绕太阳需要30年
It takes 30 years for Saturn to go around the Sun.
因此土卫六的一年 土卫六的四季
So a year on Titan, four seasons on Titan,
需要30年时间
takes 30 years.
每一季约7年之久
Each season is about seven years long.
我们想有可能在春季或雨季
We think that there might be, during the spring or the fall,
你会有大量的降雨
you get increased rainfall,
那就意味着整个北半球处在那个季节里
which means that whatever hemisphere has that season,
这样你就看到有大量的湖泊形成
actually you have a lot of lakes forming.
但是甲烷雨不同于降雨
But methane rains down differently than water,
那是由于土卫六稠密的大气层和较低的重力
thanks to Titan's thick atmosphere and low gravity.
来看看大雨滴 是地球雨滴的两倍
Think of big drops, twice the size of raindrops on Earth,
落下的速度很慢 砰 砰 砰
falling at a much slower speed, bump bump bump,
但它们极其寒冷 很冷很冷
but they'd be freezing cold, very, very cold,
要是打在你的皮肤上
if they hit your skin.
不过液态甲烷不是液态水
But liquid methane is not liquid water,
胆敢潜入甲烷湖里的人
and anyone who would dare dive into a methane lake
会感到意外
would be in for a nasty surprise.
这是我们宇宙间十分罕见的 -
It's a rare find in our universe--
一个世界 不是地球 却有着液体
a world, not Earth, that is home to a liquid.
从远处看
From a distance,
土卫六的甲烷湖似乎很熟悉和诱人
Titan's methane lakes seem so familiar and inviting,
但那确实是个化外之地
but this is truly an alien place.
首先 土卫六湖泊的温度
First, the temperature of Titan's lakes
是零下数百度
is hundreds of degrees below zero.
假如你能够适应寒冷
And assuming you could survive the cold,
在甲烷湖里游泳将是一个惊人的体验
swimming in a methane lake would be a shocking experience
完全是出乎意料的
for a totally unexpected reason.
液态甲烷的密度远小于水
The density of liquid methane is much less than water,
因此你在里头会很重
so you would be heavy in that.
你会下沉
You would sink.
我重200磅
I weigh 200 pounds.
在水中 我的实际重量接近零
In water, my effective weight is very close to zero.
在液态甲烷中 我的实际重量将会有80磅
In liquid methane, my effective weight would be 80 pounds.
想象一下试图在湖里踩水或游泳
So imagine trying to tread water in a lake or a swimming pool
绑着80磅重量
with an 80-pound weight belt tied to you.
那将是很艰难的
That's going to be hard.
那就会是在土卫六湖里游泳的情景
That's what it'd be like trying to swim in a lake on Titan.
甲烷透彻无比
Methane is so clear,
潜水员会感觉到好像透过液态空气一般
divers might feel as though they were looking through liquid air.
大部分的湖水并非如此
That's not the case in most water lakes.
不过水的不透明并不只是由于污染
But water's opacity isn't just due to pollution.
那也是水的自然特性造成的
It's also the result of a natural characteristic of water,
这对地球生命是至关重要的
which turns out to be vital for life on Earth.
这罐子是水
This pitcher is water.
我们相当熟悉水的性质了
We're familiar with the properties of water.
这里我们有液体看上去像水 但不是
Here we have a liquid that looks like water, but it's not.
这是碳氢化合物
This is a hydrocarbon.
这东西类似于土卫六上的液态甲烷
This is analogous to the liquid methane on Titan.
它们看上去一样
They look the same,
但它们的化学性质大不相同
but they have very different chemical properties.
为了显示这两种液体的不同之处
To show the difference between these two liquids,
我会拿出一些饼干
I'm going to take some crackers,
我们可以吃的东西 淀粉 糖 盐等
kind of things that we eat, starch, sugars, salt.
我要将它放到液体里
I'm going to put it in the liquids.
现在我们将饼干放到水里
So now we've got crackers in the water.
现在我取出一叠饼干
Now I'm going to take a set of crackers,
同样数量的饼干
the same number of crackers,
把它们放到液态碳氢化合物里
and I'm going to put them in our liquid hydrocarbon.
因为水能很好地溶解东西
Because water dissolves things so well,
被认为是强大的溶剂
it is considered a powerful solvent.
甲烷 那一边
Methane, on the other hand,
不能有效地溶解别的物质
can't dissolve other materials as effectively.
来看看取出的这些饼干
Look at these crackers coming out.
这饼干仍然如当初那么脆
This cracker is still as crisp as when we put it in.
这并不是很好的溶剂
This is not a very good solvent.
水的溶解能力来自其分子结构
Water's dissolving power comes from its molecular structure.
水的分子是H2O
A water molecule is H2O,
就是两个氢加一个氧
which means two hydrogens on an oxygen,
你要是去看分子的形状
and if you just think about the shape of the molecule,
你会看到你的氧原子和两个小氢原子在一头
you got your oxygen and two little hydrogens on one end.
这种结构意味着水分子的一头
This structure means that one end of the water molecule
是正电荷 而另一头则是负电荷
has a positive charge and the other has a negative charge.
因此小小的水分子
So the little water molecules
就像是小磁铁 搅动周围的东西
are like little magnets going around stirring things up,
排斥一些东西 吸引一些东西
repelling some things, attracting other things.
相比之下 甲烷是一种弱溶剂
By contrast, methane is a weak solvent.
甲烷是一个碳加上四个氢在其周围
Methane is a carbon with four hydrogens on all sides.
平均分布 没有极性
It's even. It has no polarity.
它不会分解其它分子
It won't break up other molecules.
因为水能够溶解其接触的东西
Since water dissolves what it contacts,
能够把自己变成浓汤甚至浑浊的汤
it can turn itself into a rich and sometimes murky soup.
来看这水里
So here in water,
有机物已演化到了生存在这个浓汤里了
organisms that have evolved to live in a rich soup like that,
它们微小而致密
they're going to be small and compact.
那就是我们在地球上见到的情况
And that's what we see on Earth.
微生物微小而致密
Microorganisms are small and compact.
它们能够从水里获得营养
They can get their nutrients from the water.
不过甲烷可能是另类的生命形式感兴趣的液体
But methane could be an appealing liquid for a different kind of life form.
设想一下土卫六上的生物观察地球
Imagine an organism on Titan looking at Earth
看到有液态水
and seeing the liquid water.
会惊诧于居然会有东西想生活在
It would just be appalled that anything would want to live
这样活跃 高温 具有腐蚀的液体里
in such a reactive, hot, aggressive liquid.
它会想 哎呀 地球上不可能会有生命滴
And it would think, "Jeez, there can't be life on Earth.
这种液体太难对付了
The liquid there is much too difficult to manage."
任何外星游客都有可能马上被土卫六或地球给吸引住
Any alien visitors might immediately be drawn to Titan or Earth
因为液体就在其表面流动
because liquids flow right on the surface.
有超过3亿兆加仑的水在地球上流动
Over 300 million trillion gallons of water slosh around on Earth alone.
但可能不会给星际游客就下太深刻的印象
But that might not impress interstellar travelers very much,
因为地球七大洋里没有一个是最大最深的海洋
because none of Earth's seven seas are the biggest or deepest oceans,
即使是在我们太阳系里
even in our solar system.
木星 太阳的第五颗行星
Jupiter, the fifth planet from the Sun,
隐藏着一个巨大而怪异的液体海洋
conceals an immense and bizarre liquid sea
在其神秘的云层下
beneath its mysterious clouds.
进入这种液体就需要航天器
Reaching this liquid would require a spacecraft
远超过现代科技的极限
far beyond the limits of modern technology.
必须要设法承受难以置信的压力
It would have to somehow withstand incredible pressures,
以及 更重要的是 能够经受的温度
and, more importantly, be able to stand up under temperatures
将大大超过太阳表面的温度
that are much hotter than the surface of the Sun.
是地球体积的1400倍
At 1,400 times the volume of Earth,
这颗巨星几乎是由氢和氦的气体构成的
this giant planet is mostly made up of hydrogen and helium gas.
不过在云层的深处 有一个地方
But miles and miles beneath those clouds, there's a point
大气层的重量会变得非常厉害
where the weight of that atmosphere gets so intense,
气体会变成液体
gas turns into liquid,
存在大量的液体
lots and lots of liquid.
进入液体的旅程
The journey to the liquid
始于木星大气层的外缘
begins at the outer edge of Jupiter's atmosphere,
那里的气压接近我们地球的表面
where the air pressure is close to what we experience on Earth's surface.
一头扎进木星将是个惊人的体验
Diving into Jupiter would be an amazing experience.
首先你会穿过整个上部云层
First you'd go through all these upper cloud layers,
那里有氨 甲烷及其它化合物
where there's ammonia and methane and other compounds.
它们鲜艳多彩 成漩涡状 有大量的风暴
They're really colorful and swirly, lots of storms.
色彩斑斓表示奇怪的化学混合物
The explosion of color indicates a strange brew of chemicals
夹杂着氢和氦
mixed in the hydrogen and helium.
木星大气层里有大量的各种硫化合物
There's a lot of different sulfur compounds in the atmosphere of Jupiter.
因此你穿过木星的大气层上部时
So as you fall down through the upper layers of Jupiter,
会闻到臭鸡蛋的味道
you would have the smell of rotten eggs.
因此木星之旅踏上了一段不舒服之路
So a trip to Jupiter starts off in an unpleasant way.
就像客机乘客从高空下降一样
Just like passengers on a commercial jet descending from high altitudes,
航天器里的乘客在木星大气层里下降
passengers on a spacecraft descending into Jupiter's atmosphere
会感觉到耳朵里的压力
would feel pressure on their ears.
如果你要深入到行星内部
If you go deeper into the interior of a planet,
密度会越来越大 压力会越来越大
the densities become higher, the pressures become higher.
气体会越发压缩
The gas is more compressed.
那类似于我们地球上的情景
That's similar to what we have here on Earth.
在我们大气层高处
Way up in our atmosphere,
密度和压力很低
the densities and pressures are low.
随着你往下走 它们就会增大
As you go farther down, they increase.
降落1 3万英里后 一片漆黑
After descending for 13,000 miles, it's dark,
因为阳光已无法透过这么多东西了
because sunlight can't penetrate through so much matter.
最后 黑暗消散了
At last, the darkness lifts.
光线 从木星的海洋里射出 就在下方
Light, streaming from Jupiter's ocean, lies just below.
你不会溅落在木星的这种海洋里
You don't splash down onto this sort of liquid ocean of Jupiter
如同你在地球上溅落的那样
in the same way that you splash down on Earth.
更多的像是你穿越蒸汽
It's much more like you're going through a steam
越来越浓密
that becomes denser and denser and denser
直到很难区分的高温液体
until it's indistinguishable from a very, very hot liquid.
那液体就是氢
The liquid is hydrogen.
这种热气腾腾的大海 无边无际
This steamy sea, stretching from horizon to horizon,
覆盖木星的表面
is what passes for the surface of Jupiter.
似乎难以想象 但这种液态氢的海洋
It may seem unthinkable, but this liquid hydrogen ocean
漂浮在另一种更为奇怪的液体上方
is floating above another even more bizarre liquid below it.
液体在外面的世界里很难看到
Liquids aren't easy to find on worlds outside of our own.
它们通常的形式是我们在地球上无法想象的
They often take forms we can't imagine on Earth.
那就是木星氢海洋的案例
And that's the case with Jupiter's hydrogen ocean.
貌似很陌生
Strange as it may seem,
但宇宙间最为丰富的液体却是液态氢
the most abundant liquid in the universe is liquid hydrogen.
现在事实上 某种程度上是并不陌生的
Now, in fact, in some ways that's not so strange.
氢是到目前为止宇宙间最丰富的元素
Hydrogen is by far the most abundant element in the universe.
在宇宙大多数地方
In most places in the universe,
氢分子作为气体随机游荡
hydrogen molecules are moving randomly about as a gas,
就像那些在空地里吃草的羊只
like those sheep grazing in open space.
不过木星里的环境并没有让它们自由自在
But the conditions inside Jupiter don't let them roam so freely.
不同状态下的差异
The difference between the different states
其实必定会让分子靠拢
really has to do with how closely the molecules
挤压在一起 可以这么说
are crushed together, if you will.
在地球上 我们看到液体形成于气体
On Earth, we see liquids form from gases
此时我们忽略了一杯冰水
when we leave out a glass of ice water.
暖空气接触到冰冷的杯子表面
As warm air comes in contact with the surface of the cool glass,
温度的下降消耗了气体分子的能量
the drop in temperature saps the energy of the air molecules,
从而让它们更加接近 形成液体
bringing them closer together and forming a liquid.
温度不是影响物质状态的唯一要素
Temperature isn't the only thing that affects the state of matter.
压力同样扮演了重要的角色
Pressure also plays a very important role.
压力 顾名思义 就是挤压
Pressure, as you can imagine, sort of crushes.
压力越高 把分子挤在一起就越厉害
The higher the pressure, the more it crushes molecules together
能把气体压缩成液体
and can take a gas and compress it into a liquid.
比如 即使是在太空中
For example, even in interstellar space,
零下450多度
where it's over 450 degrees below zero,
杯子里的水还会蒸发
a glass of water would just boil away.
因此当你拿上一杯水进入太空时
So when you take that glass of liquid water into space,
并不是温度 而是较低的压力
it's not the temperature, it's the low pressure
让所有的分子飞起来
that allows all the molecules to fly away
把杯子里的水变成了气体
and turn the glass of water into a gas.
木星高炉内所发生的刚好相反
The reverse occurs inside Jupiter's blast-furnace interior,
氢分子被上面大气的
where hydrogen molecules are jammed together
巨大重量挤压在一起
by the colossal weight of the atmosphere above.
一旦你将粒子压缩到晃动很小
If you squeeze the particles down so they're not vibrating very much,
它们就会彼此紧挨着
then they tend to sort of stick to one another.
它们进入了一起流动
They start flowing together.
那就是液态
That's the liquid state.
那就是为何 要是液态氢被设法立即送回地球
That's why, if liquid hydrogen were somehow instantly transported to Earth
没有足够的压力来抑制它的话
without enough pressure to contain it,
哪怕是一丁点都可以重新界定为所谓的氢弹
even a tiny bit could redefine what we think of as a hydrogen bomb.
从木星的氢海洋里舀起一杯水可不是个好主意
It wouldn't be a good idea to scoop up a cup of the liquid hydrogen from Jupiter
因为那里压力巨大
because it's under tremendous pressure.
会发生巨大的爆炸 远胜过TNT
It would be a tremendous explosive, much better than TNT.
将会是一场灾难
It would be a total disaster.
木星液体氢海洋里
Inside Jupiter's liquid hydrogen ocean,
温度超过1 7万度
it's over 17,000 degrees,
高于太阳的表面
hotter than the surface of the Sun.
深处的蓝色闪光标志了
The bluish glow at these depths signals
我们碰到了另一种液体
that we've reached another type of liquid.
它还是氢
It's still hydrogen,
但是非常特殊的形式 叫做金属液态氢
but in a very special form called metallic liquid hydrogen.
它比太阳表面更亮
It's brighter than the surface of the Sun
比太阳表面更蓝
and far, far bluer than the surface of the Sun.
这种环境是我们在地球上无法打造的
It's an environment where nothing that we can build here on Earth
是片刻都无法忍受的
could withstand that for more than a fraction of a second.
在这种极端环境中
In this extreme environment,
构成木星海洋的氢分子
the hydrogen molecules that make up Jupiter's ocean
变得活动异常怪异
start to act very strangely.
普通液态氢海洋里的分子
The molecules of the regular liquid hydrogen ocean
就像是成群结队的羊群
are like those sheep moving as a flock.
或更恰当的
Or better yet,
更像是游乐场里的情景
more like what's happening inside of an amusement park
碰碰车在溜冰场里到处乱窜
when bumper cars are streaming around a rink.
所以液体之所以成为液体
So what makes a liquid a liquid
就在于原子和分子彼此之间滑动的能力
is the ability of the atoms and molecules to slide past each other.
原子自由移动
The atoms are free to move,
它们东碰西撞 就像这些碰碰车
and they jostle around, much like these bumper cars here
在这个碰碰车场里一样
at this bumper car rink.
它们不能自由飞翔
They can't fly freely,
但是它们始终在改变邻居的位置
but they are changing their neighbors all the time.
在每一个氢原子里面
Inside each hydrogen atom,
不管是气态还是液态
whether it's in a gas or liquid form,
都有一个电子绑定在原子核上
a single electron is bound to its nucleus,
扣在它自己的原子碰碰车的驾驶座上
buckled into the driver's seat of its own atomic bumper car.
然而在木星金属液态氢的表面
But at the surface of Jupiter's metallic liquid hydrogen,
那里的压力达到了
a depth where the pressure reaches 3 million times
地球表面的300万倍
what we experience on Earth's surface,
氢分子崩溃了
the hydrogen molecules are freaking out.
液态氢实际上变成了液态金属氢
The liquid hydrogen actually becomes liquid metallic hydrogen.
现在 我所说的那个液态氢
Now, what I mean by that is that the liquid hydrogen
变得导电导热良好
starts conducting electricity and heat really well.
在木星金属液态氢里面
Inside Jupiter's metallic liquid hydrogen,
电子在分子间跳来跳去
electrons are jumping from molecule to molecule,
与自己的原子核拜拜 去找新家了
splitting away from their own nucleus and finding another home.
它们高效地带着电荷
They're carrying electric charges efficiently
从一个地方到另一个地方
from one place to another,
传递着电荷
and the transport of electric charges,
形成了电流
that's the current.
那就让电流流动了起来
That's what allows current to flow.
你肯定不想在那里的
And you sure wouldn't want to be there
要是有人放电
if someone were to discharge a big bolt of lightning
或类似的东西 因为电流
or something like that, because that electricity
会轻易穿越液态金属氢
would travel easily through the liquid metallic hydrogen,
将你杀死 把你烤死
zapping you completely, frying you.
地球上最接近金属液态氢的东西
The closest thing to metallic liquid hydrogen on Earth
是钢水
is liquid steel.
他们把钢水倒出坩埚时
When they pour the liquid steel out of the cauldron,
炙热 流动 导电
it's glowing hot, it's flowing, it's conductive of electricity.
那非常像木星内部
That's very much like the interior of Jupiter
会是你在那里的情形
would be like if you could be down there.
在木星北部 金属液态氢不同于
Inside Jupiter, the metallic liquid hydrogen is different
普通的液态氢 因为它是导电的
from the regular liquid hydrogen, because it's conducting electricity.
因此事实上 电子能够在其中自由流动
So the fact that the electrons are able to flow freely inside
意味着你可以在木星内部看到强电流
means that you can have strong electric currents in the interior of Jupiter.
要是你有液体具有强电流的话
And whenever you have a fluid that has strong electric currents,
那就会创造出一个磁场
then it will create a magnetic field.
四周方圆400万英里的空间里
For over 4 million miles of space in each direction,
木星的磁场截住并偏转在我们太阳系里
Jupiter's magnetic field scoops up and deflects charged particles
自然流动的带电粒子
that naturally course through our solar system.
不过宇宙间最大最强的磁场
But the largest and most powerful magnetic fields in the universe
是从古怪的恒星尸体中射出的 那就是中子星
shoot out from curious stellar corpses known as neutron stars.
这些磁场可能产自液体
These magnetic fields may also be generated by liquid.
不管怎样 死亡之星的内部貌似
However, the interior of a dead star seems like the last place
你预计能找到液体的最后的地方
you'd expect to find anything flowing.
中子星就好象是一大堆种子材料
A neutron star is like a big hunk of neutron material,
尽可能紧的挤压在一起
just packed as tight as it can be.
我们将其称为物质的简并
We call that matter degenerate
因为它已被压缩的紧得不能再紧了
because it can't get packed any tighter.
大多数物质 你挤压它们 就会更致密
Most materials, you push on them, they get denser.
你挤压越用力 它们就越致密
You push on them harder, they get denser.
简并物质就不一样了
Not a degenerate material.
你挤压它 再也挤不动了
You push on it, it's not going anywhere.
中子星的直径约几十英里
Neutron stars are roughly a dozen miles in diameter,
约是大城市的大小
about the size of a large city.
中子星很庞大
Neutron stars are so massive
质量被压缩在一个很小的区域里
and the mass is compressed into such a tiny region
基本上开始弯曲空间本身
that it basically is starting to warp space itself.
造访其表面是不可能的
Visiting its surface is impossible.
你用普通材料打造的所有东西
Anything that you could build out of ordinary material
都会被压扁或压碎在
would be immediately flattened and crushed
中子星的表面
on the surface of a neutron star.
中子星 引力很高
Neutron stars, the gravity is so high
甚至中子星上最高的山脉
that even the highest mountain range on a neutron star
都只能用毫米来衡量
is just measured in-- in literally millimeters.
液体会存在于如此恶劣的环境之中吗？
Could liquid possibly exist inside this hostile environment?
出人意料的是 答案有可能是肯定的
Surprisingly, the answer may be yes.
有些科学家认为中子星
Some scientists believe that neutron stars
并不是彻头彻尾的固体
are not solid to the core.
事实上 其内部有可能活动很自由
In fact, their interiors may be moving so freely,
其中有可能充满了叫做超流体的东西
they could be filled with something called superfluids,
没有稠度或粘度的液体
liquids with no thickness or viscosity.
粘度是衡量流体抵抗流动的指标
Viscosity is a measure of how resistant a fluid is to flowing.
因此低粘度的材料如水流动很容易
So a low-viscosity material like water flows very easily.
我的意思是 你可以看到它很快就流入碗里
I mean, you can see how quickly it falls into this bowl.
但是蜂蜜 这一边的 非常粘
But honey, on the other hand, is very viscous,
它流动很慢
and it flows more slowly.
流体越稠 或越粘稠
The thicker a fluid is, or the more viscous,
流动就越少
the less it flows,
其中的东西流动就越少
the less things can move around in it.
超流体具有零粘度 -
A superfluid has zero viscosity--
液体非常稀薄 流动永不停
a liquid so thin, it never stops flowing.
因此在中子星内部的怪异流体里
So in the bizarre fluid inside a neutron star,
具有我们所说的超流体性质
it has what we call a superfluid property.
因此其意思就是如果你开始搅动出一些水流
And so what that means is that if you start up some sort of current,
如果你能够在中子星内部弄出一个漩涡的话
if you're able to start up a vortex inside a neutron star,
它就会一直转啊 转个不停
then it will just keep going and going and going
不会消亡
and it won't die out.
一点都不存在粘性 让这些水流消失
There's no viscosity that causes these currents to dissolve away.
有些中子星如陀螺一般旋转 每秒转上几圈
Some neutron stars spin like tops, rotating several times every second.
就像木星上液态金属氢的情形一样
And just like the liquid metallic hydrogen works for Jupiter,
超流体内部 高能粒子到处游荡
a superfluid interior, sloshing energetic particles around,
产生出一个巨大的磁场
spawns a massive magnetic field,
只是中子星的磁场
except that a neutron star's magnetic field
要强上数百万倍
is millions of times more powerful.
我们的地球有其自己的液体在深处搅动
Our planet has its own liquid churning deep inside.
虽然没人见过它 但是地球上的生命离开了它就无法生存
Although no one has ever seen it, life on Earth wouldn't exist without it.
生命 我们知道它离开了液体将无法生存
Life as we know it wouldn't exist without liquids.
在地球上 你可能会认为水是最重要的
On Earth, you might think it's water that's most critical.
但还有一种地球液体同样至关重要
But there's another Earthly liquid that's just as vital.
地球地表以下1800英里处
1,800 miles below the Earth's surface,
温度达到了炙热的7000度
where it's a scalding 7,000 degrees,
铁水大海有一千多英里深
a sea of liquid iron over a thousand miles deep,
包裹着我们星球的固体内核
engulfs the solid inner core of our planet.
不过科学家又是如何能确定地球内部的东西的呢？
But how can scientists be sure what's inside the Earth?
这正是来自康涅狄格州丹伯里的吉娜
That's exactly what Gina S. from Danbury, Connecticut,
向《宇宙》节目提出的问题 她发短信给我们
wanted to ask "The Universe," when she texted us,
"我们是如何得知地球有一个铁核的呢
"How do we know the Earth has an iron core
而我们又从来没见过它？
"if we've never seen it?"
多谢提问 吉娜
Thanks for the question, Gina.
原来科学家往往能够间接推断事情
It turns out that scientists can often infer things indirectly,
即使他们无法直接看到它们
even if they can't see them directly.
比如 我们知道地球
For example, we know that the Earth
有一个液态的外核和一个固态的内核
has a liquid iron outer core and a solid iron inner core
因为地球有一个大磁场
because Earth has a big magnetic field,
这个液态铁核里的导电活动
and motions in this electrically conducting liquid iron core
就是产生磁场的原因
are what produce the magnetic field.
没有了磁场 地球上的生命将会遭殃
Without a magnetic field, life on Earth's surface would suffer.
要是它不存在 那么来自太阳及外太空的
If it didn't exist, then all these charged particles
所有这些带电粒子
coming from the Sun and from outer space
将会闯入我们的大气层
would go zipping through our atmosphere
影响到生命细胞
and interact with living cells,
造成大量的癌变
causing lots more cancerous mutations.
不同于地核 地球表面的环境
Unlike at the core, the conditions at the Earth's surface
把铁冻结得非常坚固
freeze iron into a solid so strong
我们在建造高大的办公楼或大桥时就要有求于它了
we turn to it when we need to construct tall office towers or long bridges.
但是在星系遥远的角落里
But in distant corners of the galaxy,
居然有世界 具有天然的高温和密度
there are worlds so naturally hot and dense
铁只不过是热气腾腾的毛毛细雨
that iron is nothing more than a steamy drizzle.
它们出现在那里 几乎被忽视和误解
They're out there, mostly overlooked and misunderstood,
作为行星则太大 作为恒星则太小
too big to be planets and too small to be stars.
它们就是所谓的褐矮星
They're known as brown dwarfs.
这些物体就像是超大版本的木星
These objects are like super-sized versions of Jupiter,
气体巨星 除了质量大出75倍
gas giants, except up to 75 times more massive.
褐矮星 某种意义上 是失败的恒星
Brown dwarfs, in a sense, are failed stars.
它们没有足够的质量在其内部产生出
They didn't have enough mass ever to produce
足够高的温度和压力
sufficiently high temperatures and pressures in their interior
去点燃普通的氢并长期燃烧
to ignite normal hydrogen and burn it for a long time.
不过这些对象还是非常炙热
But these objects are still very hot,
尽管它们的名字那样 但并不是褐色的
and despite their names, not brown.
如果你在它跟前 它发出的光
If you were right there, it would be glowing
有点像是橙红色的 大量的热量源源不断散发出来
sort of a cherry-orange red, a lot of heat coming off,
因此你会在褐矮星附近燃烧起来
so you would get burned in the vicinity of a brown dwarf.
这些对象温度很高 以至于褐矮星的云
These objects are so hot that brown dwarf clouds
并非如地球上那样由水蒸汽构成
aren't made of water vapor like on Earth,
而是气态的铁蒸汽
but rather gaseous iron vapor.
在褐矮星内部
In the interior of the brown dwarf,
压力非常之高
where the pressures are sufficiently high,
气态的铁会凝结成液体
the gaseous iron can condense into a liquid
实际上会以液态铁雨滴落下
and can actually rain down as liquid droplets of iron.
那真是好酷啊
That is really cool.
没错 褐矮星上下起了铁雨
That's right. It rains iron on brown dwarfs.
庆幸的是 我们地球上没有铁雨
Fortunately, we don't have iron rain here on Earth,
但要是我们曾有过的话 那完全就不很愉快了
but if we were to have it, it wouldn't be very pleasant at all.
就会有滚烫的铁雨滴
There'd be these hot blobs of iron
劈头盖脑落下
hitting your head and cheeks and your arms
灼伤烫伤
and burning them and scalding them.
再加上非常沉重
And plus being pretty heavy.
告诉你 你要是被快速的铁雨滴击中
You know, if you get hit by a rapidly moving droplet of iron,
那感觉就不那么好受了
that wouldn't feel very good.
液态铁从未在地球上落下过
Liquid iron never falls on Earth,
但有可能现在就在宇宙各处发生着
but it might be happening right now all across the universe.
我们星系里到处都是褐矮星
Our galaxy is really teeming with brown dwarfs.
我们星系里有数百亿颗褐矮星
There's tens of billions of brown dwarfs in our galaxy,
几乎与实际存在的恒星一样多
almost as many as there are actual stars.
不过我们的星系里也充斥着较小的世界
But our galaxy is also flooded with smaller worlds,
较多岩石 温度较低 更像地球的样子
rockier and cooler, more like Earth.
最近发生的最惊奇的事情之一
One of the most amazing things that happened recently
就是我们发现了首颗行星
is that we found the first planet
其表面或存在有水
that could potentially have water on its surface.
该行星位于围绕着名为格利泽581的恒星的太阳系里
The planet is in a solar system orbiting a star named Gliese 581,
距离地球约20光年
about 20 light-years from Earth.
其中第四颗行星 格利泽581d 轨道非常靠近其恒星
The fourth planet out, Gliese 581d, circles so close to its star
它一年就只有66天
that one of its years lasts just 66 days.
不过那是个好事情 如果我们想找到一颗行星
But that's a good thing if we want to find a planet
其表面存在水的话
with water on its surface,
因为格利泽581比我们的太阳更小更冷
because Gliese 581 is smaller and cooler than our Sun.
估算揭示了格利泽581d
Estimates have revealed Gliese 581d
其质量是地球的10倍
to be 10 times more massive than Earth,
直径是宽度的两倍
with a diameter that is twice as wide.
有些科学家认为其额外的质量
Some scientists think that what makes up that extra mass
有可能主要是气体
could be mostly gas.
那意味着格利泽581d可能类似于
That means Gliese 581d could resemble
我们太阳系里的气体巨星
the gas giants of our solar system,
如木星 土星 天王星 海王星那样
like Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune.
大量的气体 很少的液体
Lots of gas, very little liquid.
不过其他人认为格利泽581d是不一样的
But others believe that Gliese 581d is different,
更像是地球
more like Earth.
我们认为你要拼凑出10倍的地球质量
We think 10 times Earth's mass you can make up
只要将岩石材料堆在一起就行了
by just piling rocky material together.
也就是使其成为我们所谓的超级地球
So just make it something that we call a super-Earth.
它也可以是一个迷你海王星
It could be a mini-Neptune, too.
尚无定论
The jury is still out.
不过它是首个有可能像地球的东西 只是更大些
But it's the first one that could be like Earth, just bigger.
到了地球质量的10倍
At 10 times Earth's mass,
这颗外行星有可能会是一个水世界
this exoplanet may turn out to be a water world,
包裹着很深的大海
covered in a very deep ocean.
格利泽581d紧凑的轨道意味着其母星的引力
Gliese 581d's tight orbit means its parent star's gravity
始终让行星的一面面对着恒星
keeps the same side of the planet facing the star.
那就意味着行星的一半永远都没有黑夜
That means half of the planet never goes dark.
因此基本上 就是你在看月球时
So, basically, whenever you look up at the Moon,
看到的是始终月球的同一个面
you see the same side of the Moon.
那就是挨近恒星的行星所发生的情况
That would happen to a planet that close to a star.
这颗行星的一侧永远不会感觉到阳光的温暖
The far side of this planet never feels the warmth of sunlight,
有可能就是冰天雪地
leaving it potentially covered in ice.
要是你想到了这一点
If you think about that,
应该会有极端的强风
there should be extremely strong winds
从高温一侧吹向寒冷的一侧
from the hot to the cold side.
大风产生波浪 即使是在地球上
Wind creates waves, even on Earth,
劲吹的空气推拉着水面
whenever gusts of air push and pull at the water's surface.
如果格利泽581d确实是个水世界
If Gliese 581d really is a water world,
那么就没有陆地来瓦解波涛
then there's no land to break up the waves.
你有高达一英里的波涛
You have waves a mile high,
它们会愈演愈烈高达数英里
and they keep going and keep going for miles.
因此你要是喜欢冲浪的话
So if you like surfing,
那地方绝对是你求之不得的
that's definitely where you want to be.
这个超级大洋的下面可能存在硬壳
There might be a hard surface underneath this super-ocean,
但将完全不同于我们在地球上所知的一切
but it's unlike anything we know on Earth.
那是固态的水 称为七度冰(冰的立方结晶体)
It's a state of solid water known as Ice VII.
并不是羊群或碰碰车了
Instead of sheep or bumper cars,
我们把水分子看作是倒入集装箱里的一个个铝罐
let's imagine water molecules as individual aluminum cans dumped into a container.
在典型的地球温度和压力下
At typical Earth temperatures and pressures,
它们会相互错位移动 如液体一般
they interact and move together as a liquid.
它们冻结时
When they freeze,
水分子就锁在一起变成了固态的冰
water molecules lock together into solid ice.
那种水分子结构 科学家称其为一度冰
It's a molecular structure of water that scientists refer to as Ice I.
一度冰 那东西是你我司空见惯的
Now Ice I, that one that you and me are actually used to,
那只是因为没有留下太多的能量移动
this is just because it doesn't have much energy left to move
因为它已经冻住了
because it gets so cold.
水世界里的汪洋
The massive ocean of a water world
会有成百上千英里深
would be hundreds and hundreds of miles deep.
和地球上一样 水越深 压力就越大
Just like on Earth, the deeper the water, the greater the pressure.
一旦压力足够大时 有趣的事情就发生在水里了
If the pressure is great enough, something funny happens to water.
它就会变成固体 变成一种热冰
It turns solid, into a kind of hot ice.
如果你提高液体的压力
If you raise the pressure of a liquid,
通常可以将其转变成固体
you can generally turn it into a solid,
因为你将原子和分子紧紧挤压在一起
because you're squeezing the atoms and molecules
使它们束缚在一起
so close together that they feel penned in.
它们相互之间动弹不得
They can't move past one another.
它们无法流动
They can't flow.
高压能创造出各种固态冰
Higher pressures can create a variety of solid ices
其内部构造不同于冻结的冰 - 一度冰
with internal structures different from frozen ice, or Ice I.
物体之间的差异 如一度冰
The difference between anything like Ice I,
二 三 四 五 六 七度之间 -
II, III, IV, V, VI, VII--
我们认为可以一直到十度 但有可能更进一步 -
we think it goes to 10, but it could go maybe further--
实际上就是压力
is actually the pressure.
在我们习以为常的一度冰
The difference between what we're used to, Ice I,
与其他冰之间的差异就是 在其它冰里
and the other ices is that, on the other ices,
实际作用在这些罐子上的压力
there are pressures that actually act on these cans.
在这么大的行星上 水压能够达到
On a planet this big, the water pressure can reach levels
数百万倍于我们在地球上所碰到的水压
millions of times what we experience anywhere on Earth.
那就意味着 七度冰能够形成在
That means Ice VII could be forming
格利泽581d的海底
underneath the oceans on Gliese 581d.
一头扎下去 水 - 占你身体的七成
Diving down there, water-- 70% of your body--
实际上会变成冰
would actually become ice,
因此或许那不是最好的选择
so probably not the best option.
因此眼下 就目前的科学智慧
So for now, right now, technology-wise,
我们或许毫无办法下去进行探索
we probably have nothing that can go down and explore it.
但如果我们只是寻找液态水的话
But if we're just looking for liquid water,
我们完全没必要走出我们的太阳系
we don't have to travel outside our own solar system.
我们有个邻居 拥有的水量
We have a neighbor that has more water
超过了地球上所有海洋的总和
than all the oceans of Earth combined.
在液体宇宙中 木星的卫星木卫二
In a universe of liquids, Jupiter's moon, Europa,
似乎是能找到什么的难以想象的地方
appears to be an unlikely place to find some.
它是一个冰冷的荒漠
It's an arctic wasteland,
包裹着寒冰 布满了裂缝
sheathed in water ice and riddled with cracks.
它看上去貌似南极或北极的浮冰
It's like looking down on ice floes in the Arctic or Antarctic.
你看到裂缝相互交错
You see cracks that have been just offset from one another
表明其表面
and suggesting that the surface
像是漂浮在液体的上面
is kind of floating around on top of a liquid underneath.
它不只是一汪水 当然啦
And it's not just a splash of water, either.
在60英里厚的冰层下面
Beneath a layer of ice 60 miles thick
是60英里深的大海
lies an ocean 60 miles deep.
真够深的 你需要使劲钻孔
That's deep. That's a lot of drilling you would need to do
才能在木卫二上进行冰钓
if you're going to go ice fishing on Europa.
小于我们的月球
Smaller than our Moon
远离太阳近三倍
and nearly three times farther away from the Sun,
随着小小的木卫二的运行
as tiny Europa orbits,
它穿越在木星的磁场里
it passes through Jupiter's magnetic field.
但是另一个强大的木星力量
But it's another mighty Jovian force
让这个距离太阳如此遥远的世界避免了被冻成固体
that keeps a world so far from the Sun from being frozen solid.
它获得了木星引力的能量
It gets energy from the gravitational tug of Jupiter.
木星非常庞大 拉起了木卫二上的潮汐
Jupiter is very massive, and it pulls tides on Europa
就像月球拉起地球的潮汐一样
much the way the Moon pulls tides on Earth.
木星的引力与附近轨道上的其它卫星
Jupiter's gravity teams with the tugging and shoving of the other satellites
拉扯推搡 搓揉着木卫二
in nearby orbit to mash and stretch Europa.
从而产生摩擦热 熔化了卫星的内部
The resulting friction heats and melts the moon's interior.
木卫二内部整个就是盐水
What's left ground up inside Europa is saltwater.
主要是H2O 陈年纯水
It's mainly H2O, plain old water.
不过溶解于其中的是盐和其它物质
But dissolved in it are salts and other materials
就像我们的海洋里有盐 矿物质等东西
just like our ocean has salts and minerals and things
溶解在其中一样
dissolved in them.
木卫二之水的最佳比喻
The best analogy for the water on Europa
就是以色列死海里的水
would be water from the Dead Sea in Israel,
有一个很高很高浓度的盐
where you have a very, very high concentration of salts.
可不是你获取瓶装水的好地方
Not a good place to get your bottled water from.
液体可以出现在最意想不到的地方
Liquids can turn up in the most unexpected places,
但令人乍舌的莫过于
and none may be more surprising
最近所发现的液体几乎与时间本身一样古老
than a recently discovered liquid nearly as old as time itself.
140亿年前 宇宙诞生于
14 billion years ago, the universe began
一个无穷小的一点
as an infinitesimally small point
当时它迸发于一个宇宙爆发之中 即所谓的大爆炸
when it erupted in a cosmic explosion known as the Big Bang.
它迅速向外不断扩展膨胀
It rushed outward, expanding and expanding,
怪异的粒子和气体不断冷却凝聚成恒星
exotic particles and gases cooling and coalescing into stars,
接着就是太阳系 星系
then solar systems and galaxies.
不过让我们倒转时光到大爆炸后的那一刻
But let's rewind the clock to a time just after the Big Bang,
在质子和电子合并形成第一个原子之前
before protons and electrons combined to form the first atoms.
一切都在彼此碰撞
So everything was running into each other
彼此撞击
and smashing into each other,
因此所发生的情况
so that what was going on
就是没有充分的自由让粒子安顿下来
was that there wasn't enough freedom for the particles to sort of settle down
凝聚成我们现在所熟悉的东西
and clump into the things that we're familiar with now.
早期的宇宙宛如乏善可陈的沙漠
The early universe was like a featureless desert,
在上亿亿度的高温中燃烧
burning at a temperature of a million billion degrees,
铺天盖地的粒子叫做夸克和胶子
a random collection of particles known as quarks and gluons.
夸克和胶子是构成我们的
Quarks and gluons are the fundamental constituents of the nuclei
原子核的基本要素
that make up our atoms.
实际上在宇宙生命最早的百万分之十秒里
Actually in the first 10-millionth of a second of the lifetime of the universe,
曾有过一个宇宙阶段 充满了夸克和胶子
there was a phase of the universe where it was all quarks and gluons.
早期宇宙环境的最新模拟
New simulations of the conditions of the early universe
揭示了每个夸克和胶子
have revealed that the individual quarks and gluons
并不是随意乱飞 好像气体
were not flying about randomly as a gas
在那些环境中所预期的那样
as would be expected in those conditions.
相反 它们是结合在一起流动 如液体一般
Instead, they were connected and flowing like a liquid.
确切的举例就是沙子
A really good example of this is sand.
我这里拿的是一把沙子
What I have here is a handful of sand,
由很多小颗粒所构成
and it's made up of lots of little particles
基本上是小石子或石头
which are essentially like tiny rocks or stones.
然而它们相互之间的作用
But how they interact with each other
决定了它们它们相互之间一起活动
is what determines how lots of them move together
让你看到了更像是液体的流动 要远甚于
to give you something that's much more like a fluid flow
它的固体状态
than it is the behavior of a solid.
这非常像夸克和胶子在那种环境中
And so much the same thing is going on
相互碰撞的那种情形
with quarks and gluons in that situation where they're colliding.
或许同样的状态
And that was probably the same sort of behavior
就发生在宇宙的最早期
that was going on in the very early universe.
你看沙子中的模样
You'll see patterns in the sand
看上去像是洋面上的波痕
that look like ripples on the surface of an ocean
来回应 比如 风
in response, for example, to the wind,
回应的方式更多的是流体状
and responding in a way that's much more fluid-like
或液体状 多过了其作为固体
or liquid-like than it is as a solid.
波痕是某种干扰所留下的痕迹
Ripples are traces left behind by some kind of disturbance.
在物质的液态状况下
In a liquid state of matter,
波痕很容易传遍各个地方
ripples spread easily throughout the whole.
那种传递干扰的能力
That ability to communicate disturbances
可能已经对宇宙的最终命运留下了某种烙印
may have some imprint on the ultimate fate of the universe.
在其诞生后的关键的混沌时刻里
In that critical chaotic moment after its creation,
我们早期宇宙液态的流动性
the fluidity of our early universe's liquid state
就是恢宏未来的初现端倪
was already beginning to show signs of a grand future.
因此就会有部分流体
So there will be some parts of the fluid
其密度要稍大于其他部分
that are slightly more dense than other parts,
我们就能够看到开始形成的模样
and we'd be able to see patterns beginning to form
其最终所形成的结构就是我们
that will ultimately become the structure that we see
在宇宙后期所见到的
in the late universe.
流体运动被嵌入了时空结构里
Fluid motion is stitched into the fabric of space and time.
所以下次你用吸管吸汽水
So the next time you sip soda through a straw,
跳入泳池
dive into a pool,
或看到雨滴洒入水坑
or watch raindrops sprinkle into puddles,
要知道你正在用多半人生见证着我们的宇宙
know that you are witnessing our universe